and put it into the computer to edit
再放进电脑再去整修
and it just feels so cumbersome
就觉得非常费劲啊
In this episode, I'm going to talk about a very simple fact
这期我今天讲一个非常简单的一个事实
It's an issue that many scholars tend to overlook
就是很多读书人会忽略的一个问题
Speaking of Bilibili
那在B站的来讲
a lot of the users are actually college students
很多的小朋友们其实都是大学生啊
who have moved on from high school to university
他们说你从高中考上大学
to be honest
说实在的
back in high school, you didn't really
你在高中的时候其实就没有说啊
get into fights or fall in love
打架谈恋爱啊
these kinds of things happened less often
这种事干的就比较少
one particular skill might have been practiced less
其中有一项训练可能就比较少
Your skills in verbal confrontation might
就是你的骂人这方面的水平
not be as good as those with lower educational backgrounds.
可能就不如那些学历没有你高的人
However, when entering society,
但是在走向社会的时候呢
it’s still important to show a certain level of assertiveness.
还是要释放一定的攻击性的
If you’re not assertive
就是说你这个人没有攻击性
and don’t stand up for yourself,
不骂人啊
if you’re overly polite,
彬彬有礼的话
you might become everyone’s target.
你就会成为大家的一个众矢之的啊
All the tough and exhausting tasks will be assigned to you.
大家的所有的累活苦活都让你干
Why release aggression?
为什么要释放攻击性呢
It's simple.
很简单
Everyone has read 'The Prince', right?
那君主论大家都看过啊
I recommend everyone read 'The Prince'.
我推荐大家看君主论
In 'The Prince', there is a point that the cost of betraying a kind person is low. But if you want to betray someone who is extremely wicked, you need to betray them, you usually have to weigh the cost. It's the same with human society. People tend to seek benefits and avoid harm.
君主论里边就有一个 就是背叛仁慈的人的代价很小 但是你要对一个穷凶极恶的人 你要背叛他 通常要需要衡量代价 人类社会也是这样 就是说人都是趋利避害的
Once someone is particularly ruthless,
一旦一个人特别的狠
extremely fierce,
特别的凶
and downright wicked,
特别恶啊
if you think about bullying them,
你要是想欺负他的话
you need to think twice.
你就要掂量掂量
Kind people are often seen as easy targets.
而善良人是好欺负的啊
So once you're labeled as a good person,
所以说一旦你被打上了好人标签
You are helpful.
你人乐于助人
You care about your colleagues.
你这人关心同事
You are willing to contribute.
你这人甘于奉献
Then you become the one everyone relies on.
那你就是大家这个所有人都泄力的这个对象啊
No matter if you have a boyfriend or girlfriend,
不管你是交了男女朋友
people might see you as someone who can be taken advantage of.
大家也会觉得你软弱可欺
And this will continue over time.
然后可期来讲就会持续的
They will keep testing you.
就是在你身上去做试探
The first thing they test is
做试探第一件事啊
Do something trivial
干件什么小事
And then slap you
然后就扇你一巴掌
If you don’t fight back
然后你要是不反击
You still laugh it off
还跟人乐呵呵呢
People will treat you worse in the future
人家以后对你就越来越过分了
That’s just how people are
人就是这样
They bully those who are easy to bully
他就是欺负好欺负的人
No matter what kind of person
然后不论什么样的人
Regardless of good or bad
无论好坏
Regardless of strength
无论强弱
He will go out and bully others
他都会出去主动欺负人
So you don't have to take it too seriously
所以你不用太的在意这种东西
Sometimes, being the bad guy Being someone with a stronger aggressive streak No matter what Even if it's just a matter of attitude You'll find that the people who hassle you Those who make all sorts of demands on you, will suddenly decrease
所以来讲有时候作为一个恶人 作为一个攻击性比较强的人来讲 不管是怎么样 哪怕这就是做人的一个姿态 你会发现周围的人骚扰你的人啊 那个让你干各种各样事情的人一下就少了
This is also a kind of wisdom and strategy for survival.
这也是一种生存的智慧跟策略啊
It's not that we are inherently supposed to be a certain way.
并不是说我们本身就应该怎么怎么样
But in everyday life,
但是呢日常来讲
you see me often scolding people on my social media.
你看我朋友圈经常骂人
Frequently scolding people,
经常骂人来讲
surely doesn't have a good effect.
肯定效果不好啊
If leaders or teachers see it, they definitely won't think highly of it.
领导老师看见了肯定不好
But the issue is precisely this.
但那问题就是这样
My promotion
我的晋升
Does my career development require the concern of leaders and teachers?
我的事业发展需要领导老师的关心吗
No, it doesn't.
不需要
So, I don't need to respect these people in my interpersonal relationships.
所以我的人际关系里边就不需要尊重这些人啊
I have a one-on-one relationship with everyone.
我跟哪个人都是单对单的关系啊
People like me, who are so ruthless and vicious,
凡是我这样穷凶极恶的人啊
who are quick to criticize others,
没事张口就喷人的人
actually find it easier to build relationships with others.
其实反而容易跟别人建立关系
Some people might say
有人就说哎呀
Won't you alienate others this way?
那你这样不会疏远别人吗
Actually, this is still a psychological issue for humans.
其实这就是人类还是一个心理学的问题
Someone like me, who is so ruthless and vicious,
像我这样穷凶极恶
who gets furious for no reason,
闲得没事就开始火冒三丈的人
suddenly starts being nice to others,
突然之间跟别人示好啊
suddenly starts speaking to others with exceptional patience, others will feel greatly respected, because such a person with a bad temper, a person with a bad temper actually shows me such respect,
突然之间跟别人啊特别耐心的说话 别人会觉得备受尊重 因为这样一个脾气不好的人啊 一个脾气不好的人居然对我特别的礼贤下士啊
is exceptionally courteous.
特别的恭恭敬敬啊
This person is so hard to approach
明明这个人这么难接触
but he's very kind to me
但这个人对我却很温柔
he feels special about himself
他就会觉得啊自己不一样
it's like when you were in middle school
就好像你在中学时候啊
suddenly someone knows a big brother from outside school
突然谁认识一个校外的大哥
this big brother acts all high and mighty to others
这大哥对别人都人五人六的
but when you help him with his homework
但你帮大哥写作业
you find out he's really nice to you
你会发现大哥对你的特别好
and you feel really proud of it
然后你呢也特别有面子啊
Look at all of you
你看你们这些人
trembling in fear in front of the big brother
那都那个在大哥面前技若寒蝉都害怕
but when I'm in front of the big brother
但我在大哥面前
I'm his best little brother
我是我这大哥最好的小弟啊
I might not show it in front of him
在当面上可能不会那什么
but behind his back, everyone calls me the teacher
但背地里111般都管我叫老师
it's this kind of feeling
就是这种感觉
a lot of times it's like this
很多的时候都是这样
the more you seem hard to approach
你越是显得不好接触
People who interact with you will feel highly respected.
接触你的人就会觉得备受啊尊重
Exactly.
就是这样
Often times,
很多的时候呃
Let me tell you,
我跟你讲
The path of life,
这人生的路呢
is not always laid out in books.
并不是说都是书本上写好的
A lot of things are learned through practice. You'll see if it really works out in practice. Often, things don't turn out that way in practice. In practice, you often have to endure hardships. You have to face setbacks.
很多的东西都是在于实践当中 你看看实践当中是不是到底是这么回事啊 很多的时候实践当中就不是那么回事啊 实践当中很多的时候就是要受罪的 要吃亏的
You have to make compromises.
要打折扣的
Why do books write it that way?
为什么书里要那么写
Because books are for the majority.
因为书是面对大多数人的
The true experiences of a select few are different.
真正少部分人得到的经验是不一样的
So this tells you,
所以这就告诉你
Why being a good person in society
为什么在这个社会中做一个好人
is often risky.
他通常很危险
It's like being a herbivore in nature
就好像在自然界做一个食草动物一样
You don't have any aggression
你没有攻击性
You lose everything
你就没有了一切啊
Because humans are still, at heart, wild animals
因为人始终他仍然还是野兽
Still more animalistic in nature
仍然还是动物性比较强一点
Humans still have the urge to reproduce and mate
人仍然有繁殖交配
And various desires and needs for competition and conflict
战斗的各种各样的需求跟欲望
In this society
你在这个社会中
What stance do you take
你摆什么姿态
This determines what kind of species you are
你就决定了你是什么样的物种
It's the same for people
这人也是这样
First, they conform to the laws of the universe
他首先符合宇宙的法则
The laws of nature
大自然的法则
The laws of the jungle
动物园法则
And finally, human moral standards and such
最后才是人类的这些道德标准之类的
Human moral standards are for educating people
人的道德标准是为了教化人
For governing society
是为了统治社会的
To ensure that society is relatively stable, harmonious, and progresses forward
是为了让社会相对来讲稳定和谐向前发展的
He is indifferent to individual rises and falls.
他对于个体的升降
He doesn't care about them.
他是不在意的
So, a rule established by usage in society exists to ensure social stability. But when it comes to your personal development, you can't follow the norms that maintain stability. Do you understand? Because stability means no change in structure,
所以说一个社会的一个约定俗成的规矩 一定是为了社会的稳定性而存在的 而你作为个人发展来讲的话 你就不能遵从社会稳定性的东西 明白吗 因为稳定就代表着结构不变
but your personal development requires structural changes.
而你个人发展是要结构改变的
However, in a plant, nutrients move gradually from the roots up through the stem and leaves.
但是在一个植物当中的根茎叶
So you need to understand that
它的营养养分是逐渐的往上走的
from the perspective of your personal development,
所以你要明白
the way of the world is to take advantage of the situation and act against it.
从你个人的发展来讲的话
No matter what,
天下之势顺手逆取
many of my new followers,
无论怎么样啊
no matter what,
所以很多我这些新粉丝
you often have to go against conventional wisdom
无论怎么样
to achieve remarkable results.
很多的时候你都是要逆着常理来
Otherwise, you'll spend your whole life stuck in your current situation,
才能取得惊人的效果
unable to advance to a higher level.
否则你一辈子也只能就是窝在自己现在的
There's no way to move up in this class.
在这个阶级上也无法往上走